"Exercising to Protect Your
Arteries from Fast Food"
In my last video, I discussed
studies that show a single meal
high in saturated fat can impair artery
function in men, as measured in the arm,
but what we're more concerned about
is blood flow to the wall of the heart.
Researchers randomized men to
eat either a high-fat meal that was
more than 60% fat, half of it saturated,
with more than an egg's worth
of cholesterol, or a low-fat
meal that was mostly carbs
with less than 10% fat and
50 times less cholesterol.
Here's a Doppler recording of the left
anterior descending coronary artery,
known as the widow-maker,
before the high-fat meal.
Nice strong signal, squeezed
down within hours after eating.
This was taken five hours
after the high-fat meal.
The coronary flow reserve decreased
after a single high-fat meal,
but not after a low-fat meal with
the same number of calories.
What does this
coronary reserve mean?
If part of a coronary artery
is blocked for any reason,
the surrounding vessels expand.
That extra expansion capacity is
called the coronary flow reserve,
and it's clamped down within
hours of eating a fatty meal,
undermining the heart's ability to
compensate for clogged arteries.
That's how a high-fat meal
affects blood flow to the heart.
In extreme cases, you can even
witness it in the back of someone's eye.
This is the before—see the
sluggish milky-colored vessels,
and then after a low-fat diet and
drugs to help clear the fat out
of the bloodstream.
Can you see the difference?
Their blood before
looked like a milkshake.
What happens if you exercise, though,
right after that high-fat meal?
After-the-meal inflammation
following the prolonged elevation
of fat in the blood that occurs
when you eat high-fat meals,
provides a likely explanation for
increased cardiovascular disease.
But substantial evidence has
shown that acute exercise is
an effective modality for clearing
out some of that fat after a meal.
However, the benefits of acute
exercise for postprandial lipemia,
for after-the-meal fatty blood,
appear to be relatively short-lived.
Going a few days without exercising
may completely negate any benefit,
no matter how fit you are.
The time window appears to be
between 18 hours before the meal,
up until around 90 minutes
after the meal.
And how much exercise do we need?
About an hour of moderate-intensity
exercise should do it.
In this study though, it only took
20 minutes of stair climbing,
broken up into five minutes
every hour for four hours
after a McDonald's breakfast
of hash browns, eggs, pancakes,
muffins, sausage, and a milkshake.
Following such a meal, artery
function significantly decreased
when the subjects just
sat around after eating,
but not when they did the
hourly stair-climbing exercises.
In conclusion, hourly exercise may
attenuate the negative effects
not only of prolonged sitting but
also of high-fat meal intake,
suggesting that stair climbing
should be incorporated
as an easily accessible lifestyle
strategy to protect artery function.
Of course, it goes without saying
that the other way you can
protect artery-function is not
to eat breakfast at McDonald's
in the first place.
Such a meal would
also have more than
2,000 mg of sodium—more than the
1,500 the American Heart Association
recommends you stay
under for the entire day.
Give someone a meal with
even less salt, a third less,
and that alone can still impair artery
function within an hour of consumption,
even independent of the
increase in blood pressure.
When it comes to blood pressure,
some people are salt-sensitive,
meaning they suffer a large bump
in blood pressure when they eat salt.
But others are said to be salt-resistant.
Their blood pressure doesn't really
depend much on their salt intake.
So for these people is salt okay?
No. High dietary sodium intake
reduces artery function regardless
of whether your blood pressure
is salt-sensitive or salt-resistant.
Your artery function
is impaired either way,
going from a low salt diet
to a high salt diet.
See, there's an influence of dietary
salt beyond blood pressure.
In spite of the seemingly unanimous
consensus, some researchers—
too often funded by the salt industry—
claim that it's actually not good
to cut down on salt, but the evidence
is against these dissenters.
Like the saturated fat
in meat, dairy, and junk,
the science indicates that sodium,
not sodium reduction,
is the real villain.